Finding Aid for Harriet Wojtowicz papers, 1915-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harriet Wojtowicz papers 1915-2000 1938-1988
Wojtowicz, Harriet.
1 linear foot
0784 Aa 2
Spanish teacher in the Detroit Public School; personal and family documentation, letters with international correspondents, extensive travel memorabilia and other assorted documents and clippings related to Wojtowicz’s life in Detroit and numerous trips abroad.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Don Binkowski and Leonor McAlpine (donor no. 5501 ) in 2007.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born to Polish immigrants in Detroit in June of 1914, Harriet Wojtowicz graduated from Detroit's Northeastern High School in 1931. She attended the University of Michigan receiving her A.B. in 1935 and her Master's in education in 1941. Following university, Wojtowicz began working as a Spanish teacher in the Detroit Public Schools and remained employed in this capacity until the mid-1970s. In the years leading up to her retirement, however, Ms. Wojtowicz became a target of disciplinary action on the part of the Detroit School Board after her controversial decision to refuse to use the board-approved Spanish textbooks put into use in the mid-1960s, citing them as being poor tools for foreign language education and not in the best interests of her students. This event, which led to Ms. Wojtowicz being reassigned in the system, led to a publicized campaign on her behalf conducted by her colleagues and friends, and was cited at the time as sparking the first grass-roots evaluation of course materials in the history of Detroit schools.
Wojtowicz was also an extensive traveler and spent time during her early academic career studying in Mexico. In the 1950s, she took two sabbaticals from teaching to study at the Sorbonne in Paris and the University of Seville in Spain. In 1961, she was awarded a Fulbright Exchange Fellowship and spent the year teaching English in Chile. Because of these trips, and the time spent with family members still in Poland, Wojtowicz met a number of people with whom she continued to contact late into her life. The result was a large collection of correspondence from across the world in a variety of languages.
The materials in these papers detail the mid-20th century travel experiences of Detroit resident Harriet Wojtowicz. Also included are materials, which describe the family history of Wojtowicz, documents outlining the events surrounding the controversy between Ms. Wojtowicz and the Detroit Public school board in the 1960s, and a wide selection of correspondence between Wojtowicz and people in Chile, Poland, and other countries in which she traveled extensively. The collection is broken up into three series: Foreign Correspondence, World Travel Materials, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Wojtowicz, Harriet.; Detroit Public Schools.; Polish American women--Michigan--Detroit.; Textbooks--Michigan--Detroit.; Travelers--Poland.; Travelers--Chile.; Teachers--Michigan--Detroit.
Contributors:
Alzona, Encarnación, 1895-; Starkie, Enid.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Foreign correspondence
  The Foreign Correspondence series begins with two folders containing letters from specific individuals that Harriet Wojtowicz befriended in her travels. The first of these comes from Encarnación Alzona, who is widely recognized as being the first female historian of the Philippines. The second folder is a collection of correspondence with and clippings about Irish literary critic Enid Starkie. The remainder of the series is organized geographically with two folders of letters sent from friends and family in Poland, and one folder each originating from Chile, England and France. There is a further miscellaneous folder that ends the series, which features letters sent to Ms. Wojtowicz from a variety of countries.
  - With Encarnación Alzona (Box 1)
  - With Enid Starkie (Box 1)
  - Polish
    - Undated 1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1999 (Box 1)
  - Chilean
    - 1961-1988 (Box 1)
  - English (Box 1)
  - French (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- World travel materials
  The second series, World Travel Materials, is an assortment of items collected and saved by Wojtowicz throughout the course of her numerous international trips in the 1930s through the 1960s. The materials included in the folders of this series include numerous photographs taken by or of Wojtowicz, passports and other travel documentation used on these trips, and memorabilia items collected abroad.
  - Mexico, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Guatemala, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Europe, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Paris, Berlin and Poland, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Chile, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Poland, Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Dated (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Scrap Books
    - Europe, 1938 (Box 1)
    - United States, Bermuda, and Mexico, 1939 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series, which concludes the collection, consists of four folders documenting other aspects of Harriet Wojtowicz's life in Detroit. The first of these contains documents and photos related to her early family life, including a number of papers, which shed a little light on the story of her parents as Polish Immigrants in Detroit in the early twentieth century. The second folder is a lengthy assortment of correspondence and documents related to Wojtowicz's refusal to use a board-mandated Spanish textbook in her classroom in the mid-1960s, the controversy that followed, and her attempts to be re-instated in her former position and have the rating of "unsatisfactory" removed from her faculty record. The remaining folder is a brief assortment of personal documents shedding light on Wojtowicz's biography, and the final folder is a collection of personal portraits of Harriet Wojtowicz.
  - Family History (Box 1)
  - Detroit Public Schools Spanish Textbook Controversy (Box 1)
  - Biographic Materials (Box 1)
  - Photographic portraits (Box 1)